Finding Aid for Computing Center (University of Michigan) records, 1952-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- MTS (Michigan Terminal System)
  The MTS series contains digital surrogates (in PDF format) of documents already held at the Bentley Library as well as source code and documentation of the six full and the ten partial MTS distributions (and two redistributions) created between 1968 and 1988. The distribution documentation covers versions 1.0 to 6.0; distributions 1.0 through 3.1 supported the IBM S/360 Model 67, distribution 3.2 supported both the IBM S/360-67 and the IBM S/370 architecture, and distributions D3.3 through D6.0 supported just the IBM S/370 architecture and its extensions. The D6.0 distribution materials are suitable for the creation of an IPLable version of MTS based upon the version that was in use at the University of Michigan in 1996 shortly before MTS was shutdown. These files are accompanied by a labeled tape (lbltp) program that may be used to read and decode the MTS source code on Windows, Mac OS, and Unix computers. The scanned documents in the series include Computing Center memos, reference documents, MTS user manuals, and internal system documentation (used by system programmers).
  - Distribution Documentation (digital) 1968-1988
    - Distribution 1.0 1968
      - Log File and 10 Line Listing
      - Modification 1, Log File and 10 Line Listing
    - Distribution 2 1970
      - Distribution 2.0 Log File and 10 Line Listing
      - Distribution 2.1 Notes and Log File
      - Distribution 2.2 Log File, 10 Line Listing, and Driver File Listing
      - Distribution 2.3 Log File
    - Distribution 3 1973
      - Distribution 3.0
        - Log File
        - Notes and Driver File
      - Distribution 3.1
      - Distribution 3.2
    - Distribution 4 1977
      - Distribution 4.0
        - Log File
        - Notes and Driver File
      - Distribution 4.1 Driver File, Index, Notes, and Log
      - Distribution 4.2 Driver File, Index, Notes, and Log
      - Distribution 4.2A (Redistribution 16) Driver File and Log File
      - Distribution 4.2B Log File, Driver File, and MTS Forum
      - Distribution 4.3 Driver File, Index, Notes, and Log
    - Distribution 5 1981
      - Distribution 5.0
        - Change Forms
        - Driver File, Index, Notes, and Log
      - Distribution 5.1
        - Index
        - Driver File, Notes, and Log
        - Log
    - Distribution 6.0 1988
      - Notes, Newsys, Oldsys, MTS Doc, and Index
      - Driver File List
      - Log
    - Distribution lbltp program 2011
    - Distribution copyright statement and notes 2011
  - Computing Center Memos 1988
    - No. 480: Translation Day Character Code Changes on MTS February 1988
    - No. 815: Using LaTeX on Michigan Terminal System August 1988
  - Internal System Documentation 1978-1995
    - Disk Disaster Recovery April 1987
    - Lecture 1 May 1978
    - MTS D6.0 Disk Documentation April 1987
    - MTS Operators Manual February 1995
    - Resource Manager Operations Manual March 1990
    - University of Michigan Multiprogramming Supervisor (UMMPS) Supervisor Call Descriptions (MTS Distribution 6.0) November 1987
    - Volume 01: Michigan Termal System (Systems Edition) November 1991
    - Volume 03: Systems Subroutine Descriptions (Systems Edition) April 1981
    - Volume 99: Collected Materials June 1978
  - Manuals
    - GOM (Good Old MAD) 1989
      (language description and usage information)
    - MTS Volumes 1967-1993
      - MTS Second Edition Volume I December 1967
      - MTS Second Edition Volume II December 1967
      - MTS Volume 01: The Michigan Terminal System November 1991
      - MTS Volume 02: Public File Descriptions May 1990
      - MTS Volume 02X: Obsolete Public File Descriptions January 1987
      - MTS Volume 03: System Subroutine Descriptions September 1989
      - MTS Volume 04: Terminals and Networks in MTS July 1988
      - MTS Volume 05: System Services September 1985
      - MTS Volume 06: FORTRAN in MTS February 1988
      - MTS Volume 07: PL/I in MTS September 1985
      - MTS Volume 08: LISP and SLIP in MTS January 1983
      - MTS Volume 09: SNOBOL4 in MTS January 1983
      - MTS Volume 10: BASIC in MTS December 1980
      - MTS Volume 11: Plot Description System April 1985
      - MTS Volume 12: PIL/2 in MTS December 1974
      - MTS Volume 13: Symbolic Debugging System September 1985
      - MTS Volume 14: 360/370 Assemblers in MTS September 1986
      - MTS Volume 15: FORMAT and TEXT360 March 1988
      - MTS Volume 16: ALGOL in MTS September 1980
      - MTS Volume 17: Integrated Graphics System September 1984
      - MTS Volume 18: The MTS File Editor February 1988
      - MTS Volume 19: Magnetic Tapes October 1993
      - MTS Volume 20: Pascal in MTS January 1989
      - MTS Volume 21: MTS Command Extensions and Macros April 1991
      - MTS Volume 22: UTLisp in MTS May 1988
      - MTS Volume 23: Messaging and Conferencing in MTS February 1991
    - University of British Columbia Computing Centre (PLUS programming language and Command Language Parser) 1982-1987
      - CLPARSER: A Command Language Parsing Facility November 1982
      - PLUS Source Library Definitions January 1983
      - PLUS: The Plus Programming Language October 1987
  - Reference Documents 1986-1995
    - BITNET on Michigan Terminal System September 1990
    - C89 S/370 compiler October 1992
    - Computer Conferencing Guidelines October 1989
    - Confer and Michigan Terminal System Help October 1989
    - Guidelines for Effective Conferencing for Organizers October 1989
    - Guidelines for Effective Conferencing for Participants October 1989
    - Information Technology Division Publications November 1995
    - TEXTFORM Reference Manual January 1986
    - The Resource Manager November 1991
- Online Discussions 1978-1996
  (BHL deposit ID 9551_0003)
  [SR RESTRICTED until January 1 2086 ]
  - Confer
  - MNET Caucus and Staff
  - *Forum
- Archived Website
  The Archived Website series consists of a web captures of a Michigan Terminal System Archive website created by Jeff Ogden and administered by former computing center employees Ogden, Gavin Eadie, and Mike Alexander. The site includes news and information related to MTS and related projects. Starting in 2011, versions of this website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - Michigan Terminal System Archive, 2011-
Related Material
Material at the Bentley Historical Library related to computing at the University of Michigan and the Computing Center record group includes the following:
Information Technology Division records
University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization records
Logic of Computers Group records
Merit Network records
Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research records
Arthur W. Burks papers
Bernard Galler papers
Aaron Finerman papers
Additional units that were early involved in utilizing information technology and / or providing information technology services include: Medical School, Survey Research Center (ISR), College of Engineering, University Library, School of Business Administration, Economics Department, School of Information, and College of Literature, Science and the Arts.
Bibliography
A group of former MTS developers have created a website, the Michigan Terminal System Archive documenting the history of MTS. It includes links to many of the publications and documents included in the Computing Center Records group.
Brief historical sketches of the development of MTS and the Merit Network are available online at:
In Information Technology Digest, May 13, 1996
"A History of MTS: Thirty Years of Computing Services" [http://www.60bits.net/msu/mycomp/mts/others/feat01.htm accessed 5/28/20152]
"MTS Fostered Creation of Computing Community" [http://www.60bits.net/msu/mycomp/mts/others/feat01.htm accessed 5/28/2015
"MTS: Thanks for the Memories" [http://www.60bits.net/msu/mycomp/mts/others/feat03.htm accessed 5/28/2015
"MTS Timeline" [http://archive.michigan-terminal-system.org/discussions/timeline accessed 5/28/20152
Merit Website
History / Timeline
includes links to the following articles:
"Merit - Who, What, and Why" by Eric Aupperle
"A Chronicle of Merit's Early History" by John Mulcahy